# Rubens Pessoa

#### SENIOR IOS SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Graz. Austria

📳 +4367763041761 | 🗷 contact@rubenspessoa.dev | 🧥 www.rubenspessoa.dev | 🖸 github.com/rubenspessoa | 🛅 linkedin.com/in/rubenspbf

## **Personal Profile**

An accomplished Senior iOS Software Engineer that brings 6 years of experience in developing, launching, and maintaining mobile applications across a range of industries, including communications, banking, healthcare, hospitality, and transportation. Currently enrolled in the Master's program in Software Engineering and Management at Technische Universität Graz, is dedicated to enhancing his skills and knowledge to deliver world-class products. With a proven track record in problem-solving, teamwork, and attention to detail, is committed to creating exceptional mobile applications that meet the needs of businesses and users alike.

## **Education**

#### **Technische Universität Graz**

Graz, Austria

MSc in Software Engineering and Management

March 2023 - Current

- Major in Intelligent Systems
- Minor in Industrial Management and Innovation

#### Universidade Federal de Alagoas

Maceió, Brazil

BSc in Computer Science

January 2014 - January 2018

## **Work Experience**

iTranslate GmbH Graz, Austria

iOS Software Engineer

June 2021 - April 2023

- Contributed to the company's overall product development using Swift and the UIKit and SwiftUI frameworks.
- Used MVVM (Model-View-ViewModel) and MVVM+C (Model-View-ViewModel + Coordinators) structural design patterns to create a testable code
   base
- Implemented Unit Tests using XCTest.
- · Designed Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery (CI/CD) infrastructure on the Bitrise platform.
- Implemented A/B Tests so the product team could make data driven decisions based on screen performances.
- Used several Apple frameworks such as Vision, Core Data, Core Haptics, DeviceCheck, and NaturalLanguage.
- Improved iOS, WatchOS apps' and App Extensions' code bases by refactoring opportunistically and fixing bugs.
- Used Xcode's Instruments to discover and fix memory leaks throughout the app.
- Created and maintained proprietary libraries following the SOLID and DRY principles.
- Included third-party libraries via CocoaPods and SPM (Swift Package Manager).
- · Using URLSession, developed the client-side of a REST APIs that connected with the backend via HTTP or WebSocket connections.
- Improved app's visibility on AppStore (i.e improved App Store Optimization) by implementing capabilities released on latest WWDC events (for example: lock screen widgets).
- Researched newly released technologies at WWDC and engineered proof-of-concepts that were later included into the products' roadmaps.
- · Used SCRUM as the main agile methodology. Took part in daily, retro, planning, refinement and estimation meetings.
- Used the GitFlow's branching model. Reviewed and shared knowledge on Pull Requests.
- Key Achievement: Implemented the iTranslate's iOS app redesign. After one month of wide-spread adoption, 99,0% of the users were
  crash-free according to Firebase's Crashlytics.

Grüv.it (Self-employed) Graz, Austria

iOS Software Engineer

October 2022 - December 2022

- Contributed to the development of the social network, along with its game mechanism using Swift and the UIKit framework.
- · Using URLSession, developed the client-side of a REST APIs that connected with the Backend via WebSocket connections..
- Created and Maintained UI Interfaces through the Interface Builder (Storyboards and Xib files).
- Managed releases and TestFlight builds on App Store Connect.
- Used the GitFlow's branching model

APRIL 10, 2023

iOS Software Engineer February 2019 - May 2021

- Contributed to the development of iOS Applications in the Banking and Health Industries using the UIKit and SwiftUI frameworks.
- Implemented UI Tests using XCTest.
- Included third-party libraries such as CoreStore, Apollo Client, Moya, KingFisher and Lottie via Cocoapods.
- · Contributed to the development of a Backend-for-Frontend (BFF) application using NestJS framework and GraphQL in the Banking industry.
- · Contributed to the development of a Progressive Web Application (PWA) using React and Redux in the Hospitality industry.
- Actively participated in the entire lifecycle of multiple client projects, starting from ideation and conceptualization to their ultimate deployment on the AppStore.
- Used SCRUM as the main agile methodology. Took part in daily, retro, planning, refinement and estimation meetings.
- · Used the GitFlow's branching model. Reviewed and shared knowledge on Pull Requests.

## CloudTaxi (Self-Employed)

Maceió, Brazil

iOS Software Engineer

April 2018 - August 2018

- Contributed to the development of Cloudtaxi's iOS Application using Swift and the UIKit framework.
- Acted as a product manager by defining roadmaps after meeting with the client and other teams.
- Created and Maintained UI Interfaces through the Interface Builder (Storyboards and Xib files).
- Managed releases and TestFlight builds on App Store Connect.

#### Ilhasoft Tecnologia da Informação Ltda.

Maceió, Brazil

iOS Software Engineer

November 2017 - April 2018

- Contributed to the development of multiple client projects. Worked as an iOS Developer using mainly Swift and the UIKit framework.
- Created and maintained UI Interfaces through the Interface Builder (Storyboards and Xib files).
- Used Kanban as the main agile methodology. Took part in daily meetings.

#### Ilhasoft Tecnologia da Informação Ltda.

Maceió, Brazil

Internship - iOS Software Engineer

April 2017 - October 2017

- Contributed to the development of an open-source project from UNICEF called UReport. Worked on the iOS Application using Swift, Objective-C and the UIKit framework.
- Created and maintained UI Interfaces through the Interface Builder (Storyboards and Xib files).
- Used Kanban as the main agile methodology. Took part in daily meetings.

## Skills

Swift Programming Language (UIKit, SwiftUI, CoreData, Vision, CoreHaptics, DeviceCheck, Natural Language, XCTest), HTTP

Programming protocol, Websocket protocol, REST API (client implementation), GraphQL, Javascript and Typescript (React and NestJS),

HTML/CSS, SQL, Objective-C, Python, R

Miscellaneous Xcode, Xcode Instruments, Cocoapods, Swift Package Manager (SPM), Git, Github, Jira, Confluence, Bitbucket, Firebase, Shell

(Bash/Zsh), ETFX(Overleaf)

**Soft Skills** Adaptability, Problem-solving, Time Management and Teamwork.

#### Achievements

2017 **Hackathon Winner - Economiza Alagoas Category**, 1° Hackathon Insano SEFAZ/AL Alagoas, Brazil

2013 **Gold Medal**, Olympiads in Informatics - Advanced Junior Category

Paraíba, Brazil

## Languages\_

Brazilian Portuguese Native Proficiency

**English** Professional Working Proficiency - IELTS Academic 2022 Grade 7 - CEFR C1

**German** Elementary Proficiency - CEFR A2

**Spanish** Elementary Proficiency

APRIL 10, 2023 2